<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Jesse&#39;s blog</title>
  
  <subtitle>Jesse 的小窝</subtitle>
  <link href="https://www.jessexu.me/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="https://www.jessexu.me/"/>
  <updated>2021-04-23T06:49:56.000Z</updated>
  <id>https://www.jessexu.me/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Jesse Xu</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="https://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Week 2 - Image Preprocessing</title>
    <link href="https://www.jessexu.me/basis-senior-project/week2/"/>
    <id>https://www.jessexu.me/basis-senior-project/week2/</id>
    <published>2021-04-22T09:11:31.000Z</published>
    <updated>2021-04-23T06:49:56.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello everyone, welcome to my blog again. It has been a busy week for me, and I did some work to preprocess the images for recognition. </p><h2 id="See-my-work"><a href="#See-my-work" class="headerlink" title="See my work!"></a>See my work!</h2><p>In order to give you a clearer idea of what I did, I put some extra efforts to put my work as an web app using the free hosting service Heroku (huge thanks to them!), so that you can get your hands on and experiment with the program I wrote. You may find it here: <a href="https://senior-project.jessexu.me/?file_selection=Week+2">https://senior-project.jessexu.me/?file_selection=Week+2</a> (loading time may be a bit long because the images are being processed in real-time, and make sure you have good Internet)</p><h2 id="What-does-the-program-do"><a href="#What-does-the-program-do" class="headerlink" title="What does the program do?"></a>What does the program do?</h2><p>You may be a bit confused if you head straight into the web app above, so let me explain what is the program I wrote this week doing. </p><p>I will use the parameters that I set as the default of the app when I’m explaining. They turn out to produce pretty good results after I experimented with them. </p><p> <img src="/img/bigz-senior-project-week2.assets/image-20210422173039847.png" alt="Default Parameters"></p><center>Default parameters<center/><p>Let’s start with the original image. It’s a photo of a part of the gyroscope. As mentioned in last week’s blog post, the preprocessing I need to apply on the photo is to denoise the image, find the contours of the part (in this photo’s case, the contours of the broaches/combs), and find the corners of the parts. </p><img src="/img/bigz-senior-project-week2.assets/image-20210423093322870.png" alt="Original image" style="zoom:50%;" /><p>First, we need to turn it into a grayscale image for further processing. OpenCV has a handy method for this: </p><figure class="highlight python"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">gray = cv2.cvtColor(img, cv2.COLOR_BGR2GRAY)</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><img src="/img/bigz-senior-project-week2.assets/image-20210423114958615.png" alt="Grayscale image" style="zoom:50%;" /><p>Then, we can filter out some of the noise in the photo to get a clearer shot by first dilating then eroding the image. It can be done with the following two lines of code. With higher iterations, more noise will be filtered out, but it may also distort the image. </p><figure class="highlight python"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">kernel = np.ones((<span class="number">3</span>, <span class="number">3</span>), np.uint8) <span class="comment"># We use a commonly used 3x3 kernel for this.</span></span><br><span class="line">dilated_img = cv2.dilate(gray, kernel, iterations) <span class="comment"># gray is the grayscale image.</span></span><br><span class="line">eroded_img = cv2.erode(dilate_img, kernel, iterations)</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><img src="/img/bigz-senior-project-week2.assets/image-20210423115652416.png" alt="Dilation and erosion" style="zoom:50%;" /><p>Then, we can apply a threshold to the image with the following code to get a binary image from the de-noised image. You can see that one of the dirty points that did not get removed from previous processes was retained in the threshold processed image. </p><figure class="highlight python"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">cv2.threshold(erosion, threshold_value, <span class="number">255</span>, cv2.THRESH_BINARY)</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><img src="/img/bigz-senior-project-week2.assets/image-20210423120048713.png" alt="threshold" style="zoom:50%;" /><p>With the binary image we have, we can get the contour of the shapes with the code below and draw it out. As you can see, the contours are quite clear.</p><figure class="highlight python"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">contours, hierarchy = cv2.findContours(binary_image, cv2.RETR_TREE, cv2.CHAIN_APPROX_SIMPLE)</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><img src="/img/bigz-senior-project-week2.assets/image-20210423141418895.png" alt="contours" style="zoom:50%;" /><p>Lastly, we run a Hough Line Transform to detect the lines in the contours image, so we can find the corners and dimensions of the shapes. The code used here is </p><figure class="highlight python"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">lines = cv2.HoughLinesP(img, <span class="number">1</span>, np.pi/<span class="number">180</span>, <span class="number">100</span>,minLineLength=<span class="number">100</span>, maxLineGap=<span class="number">10</span>)</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><img src="/img/bigz-senior-project-week2.assets/image-20210423142525498.png" alt="Hough Line Transform Result" style="zoom:50%;" /><p>However, the results I get here is not very impressive, as it detects way more lines than it should, and there are small line segments clustered together if you zoom in the image. So, I will focus on fine-tuning the parameters for the Hough Line Transform next week. </p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone, welcome to my blog again. It has been a busy week for me, and I did some work to preprocess the images for recognition. &lt;</summary>
      
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Basis" scheme="https://www.jessexu.me/tags/Basis/"/>
    
    <category term="Senior Project" scheme="https://www.jessexu.me/tags/Senior-Project/"/>
    
    <category term="English" scheme="https://www.jessexu.me/tags/English/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Week 1 - Intro to the project</title>
    <link href="https://www.jessexu.me/basis-senior-project/week1/"/>
    <id>https://www.jessexu.me/basis-senior-project/week1/</id>
    <published>2021-04-13T08:21:14.000Z</published>
    <updated>2021-04-14T01:53:33.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hi everyone, thanks for your interest in my project. As mentioned in the project abstract, my project will focus on creating a program that recognizes and calculates the dimensions of parts in a MEMS gyroscope that needs to be etched with a laser from photos taken by a microscope camera. The program will then be put together with the works of other colleagues on the site to achieve the goal of automating the gyroscope-fixing process.  </p><h2 id="What-tools-will-I-use"><a href="#What-tools-will-I-use" class="headerlink" title="What tools will I use?"></a>What tools will I use?</h2><img src="/img/bigz-senior-project-week1.assets/image-20210413163329340.png" alt="image-20210413163329340" style="zoom: 33%;" /><p><strong>OpenCV</strong> is a powerful and widely used image processing library for computer vision. It has a lot of built-in functions that allow developers to easily apply different effects and calculations on images. Since this project is focused on creating a program that deals with photos of a gyroscope, OpenCV will be the core of this project. </p><p>As for the choice of programming language, I chose <strong>Python</strong> as it is succinct and easy-to-use, so that I can focus on developing the algorithm for processing the images instead of wasting time on dealing with programming issues. Also, Python has great support and integration for OpenCV through the <code>opencv-python</code> library, it can be installed easily on any computer that has a python environment with a single line of command: <code>python -m pip install opencv-python</code>.</p><p>For creating an intuitive GUI (graphical user interface) program, I went with <strong>Streamlit</strong>, an awesome library in Python that offers a simple way to create web apps. It has plenty of built-in widgets such as sliders, buttons, and select-boxes that will come in handy when I need to tweak the parameters of image-processing functions.</p><h2 id="What-do-the-images-look-like"><a href="#What-do-the-images-look-like" class="headerlink" title="What do the images look like?"></a>What do the images look like?</h2><p>So what do the parts in a MEMS gyroscope look like, you may ask. Well, here’s a sneak peek at some sample images of it taken by a microscope camera. As you can see from the image below, parts in a gyroscope can be roughly categorized into three categories: triangles, rectangles, and broaches/combs. Recognizing these shapes and their dimensions will be one of the major goals of this project.</p><p>It may sound easy, but it is in fact quite hard to write a program with the aforesaid functionality. From my prior research, the rough process will be: denoising the images; finding the contours of the parts; finding the corners of the shapes; calibrating the image-to-reality scale; and computing the real sizes of the parts according to the scale. </p><p><img src="/img/bigz-senior-project-week1.assets/image-20210413162931134.png" alt="Images of a MEMS gyroscope"></p><p>That’s all for this week. Next week, I will start to apply some preprocessing to the images and try to find the contours of the gyroscope parts in the images. Stay tuned! </p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi everyone, thanks for your interest in my project. As mentioned in the project abstract, my project will focus on creating a program th</summary>
      
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Basis" scheme="https://www.jessexu.me/tags/Basis/"/>
    
    <category term="Senior Project" scheme="https://www.jessexu.me/tags/Senior-Project/"/>
    
    <category term="English" scheme="https://www.jessexu.me/tags/English/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Jesse Jiaxi Xu&#39;s senior project - &quot;Make Computers See - Image Processing with OpenCV&quot;</title>
    <link href="https://www.jessexu.me/basis-senior-project/en/abstract/"/>
    <id>https://www.jessexu.me/basis-senior-project/en/abstract/</id>
    <published>2021-04-04T14:51:04.000Z</published>
    <updated>2021-04-14T01:50:02.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="Abstract-for-the-project"><a href="#Abstract-for-the-project" class="headerlink" title="Abstract for the project"></a>Abstract for the project</h3><p>MEMS gyroscopes are a type of sensor that is widely used in phones, cars, and many other devices to detect the rate of rotation. However, the mass production units of the gyroscope may be imprecise due to errors in production. One may need to fine-tune the gyroscopes to achieve higher precision. It can be accomplished by precisely etching parts of it with a laser. To automate the process, photos of the gyroscope will be taken with a microscope camera; a computer program will then recognize parts to be fixed and calculate the actual area to be fixed from the image taken; another program will use the results of the previous program and control the laser etching machine to etch the gyroscope. This project will focus on creating the computer program that recognizes and calculates the parts in the gyroscope to be fixed, and it will integrate with other colleagues’ programs to achieve the overarching goal. OpenCV is an image processing library that will be used in this project to process the image, and the processing algorithm will be implemented with the Python programming language. The major process of the project is to find the contours of parts in the gyroscope; identify certain shapes that make up the gyroscope; calculate the parts to be etched according to the image scale. </p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
    <summary type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;Abstract-for-the-project&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Abstract-for-the-project&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Abstract for the project&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Abstract for t</summary>
      
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Basis" scheme="https://www.jessexu.me/tags/Basis/"/>
    
    <category term="Senior Project" scheme="https://www.jessexu.me/tags/Senior-Project/"/>
    
    <category term="English" scheme="https://www.jessexu.me/tags/English/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Jesse Jiaxi Xu 的毕业生项目：“计算机视觉：基于 OpenCV 的图像处理”</title>
    <link href="https://www.jessexu.me/basis-senior-project/zh/abstract/"/>
    <id>https://www.jessexu.me/basis-senior-project/zh/abstract/</id>
    <published>2021-04-04T14:51:04.000Z</published>
    <updated>2021-04-14T01:50:02.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="项目摘要"><a href="#项目摘要" class="headerlink" title="项目摘要"></a>项目摘要</h3><p>MEMS陀螺仪是一种广泛用于手机、汽车等许多设备中的传感器芯片，它可以检测旋转速度。然而，这种陀螺仪的量产单元可能会因为生产中的误差而不精确，人们可能需要对陀螺仪进行微调以达到更高的精度。这种需求可以通过用激光精确地蚀刻陀螺仪的部分来实现。为了实现这一过程的自动化，陀螺仪的照片会用显微镜相机拍摄；然后，一个计算机程序将识别需要修调的部件，并根据拍摄的图像计算出实际需要修调的面积；另一个程序将使用前一个程序的结果，控制激光蚀刻机对陀螺仪进行蚀刻。本项目的重点是创建能够识别和计算陀螺仪中需要修调的部分的计算机程序，并与我所工作的地方的其他同事的程序相结合，以实现总体目标。OpenCV是一个图像处理库，在本项目中，我将使用OpenCV对图像进行处理，处理算法将用Python编程语言实现。项目的主要过程是找到陀螺仪中零件的轮廓，识别出构成陀螺仪特定部分的形状，以及根据图像比例计算出需要蚀刻的部分。</p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
    <summary type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;项目摘要&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#项目摘要&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;项目摘要&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;项目摘要&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;MEMS陀螺仪是一种广泛用于手机、汽车等许多设备中的传感器芯片，它可以检测旋转速度。然而，这种陀螺仪的量产单元可能会因为生产</summary>
      
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Basis" scheme="https://www.jessexu.me/tags/Basis/"/>
    
    <category term="中文" scheme="https://www.jessexu.me/tags/%E4%B8%AD%E6%96%87/"/>
    
    <category term="Senior Project" scheme="https://www.jessexu.me/tags/Senior-Project/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>杰西讲故事 - 高中语文毕业总结</title>
    <link href="https://www.jessexu.me/bigz2021.html"/>
    <id>https://www.jessexu.me/bigz2021.html</id>
    <published>2021-03-24T14:49:55.000Z</published>
    <updated>2021-04-13T15:21:56.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="写在前面"><a href="#写在前面" class="headerlink" title="写在前面"></a>写在前面</h3><p>一开始让我做这个毕业项目的时候我是毫无头绪的，看同学们各种各样的项目，我真的想不到我能做些什么——有的同学给所有人都定制一份带有自己特色的东西，我没可能给每个同学写一段代码吧？于是，我就打算跟随我的记忆，想到哪写到哪，把我在高中这 4 年时光粗浅地写出来。</p><p>有些地方我可能颇有感触，但是由于我不太善于表达，我可能无法把我全部的情感都写出来。如果你是我写到的一位朋友，而我没有把一些重要的细节写出来，请见谅！</p><h3 id="我与朋友们"><a href="#我与朋友们" class="headerlink" title="我与朋友们"></a>我与朋友们</h3><h4 id="凌宇骏"><a href="#凌宇骏" class="headerlink" title="凌宇骏"></a>凌宇骏</h4><p><img src="img/%E6%9D%B0%E8%A5%BF%E8%AE%B2%E6%95%85%E4%BA%8B.assets/QQ%E5%9B%BE%E7%89%8720210324230353.jpg" alt="和凌宇骏在吃椰子鸡"></p><p>作为我在贝赛思最好的朋友之一，当然要有些牌面的，我就第一个来写好了。我和凌宇骏的相遇还挺魔幻的。在青涩的九年级，我还什么朋友都没有的时候，突然有个 spirit week，要求穿 “twins” 装。当我还在纠结的时候，我妈跟我说，你们年级有个和你一样从省附转过来的，叫凌宇骏，不如你去找他跟你一起穿校服吧。于是就有了这么一段在 Mr. Kight 教室门口的储物柜前的尴尬对话：</p><p>“你是凌宇骏吗？”（在此处脑补徐嘉曦紧紧张张半天说不出一句话的样子）</p><p>“是啊，怎么了？”</p><p>“你是省附的吗？”</p><p>“是…？”</p><p>“那下周 twins day 我们一起穿省附校服？”（此时我自己也意识到了问这件事是多么的尴尬了）</p><p>“哦，好啊。”</p><p>就这样，我和这个本来性格上还是兴趣爱好上似乎都八竿子打不着的 John 认识了。这么说来，也真是缘分啊。</p><img src="/img/杰西讲故事.assets/Screenshot_20210321-175703_cr.jpg" alt="和John的友谊巨轮" style="zoom: 25%;" /><p>在这四年里，我们俩各种打打闹闹，莫名就玩在一块了。到现在我都不知道除了同是省附校友之外，到底还有什么东西让我们俩的友谊走到现在的样子的。大概是<del>我一直赖着他</del>时间的力量吧。不过，我还是非常感谢凌宇骏陪我度过那么好的一段时光，尤其是他一直那么放纵我的任性（比如我连续两年都强行拉着他进我的俱乐部，现在想想挺野蛮的哈哈哈）。许多人对他的印象都是“对女生很 gentle，对男生很狂暴”，但我感觉他似乎对我是例外，对我挺奈斯的。这几年真的一起玩得很开心。希望以后也要一起玩下去啊~</p><h4 id="吴文萱"><a href="#吴文萱" class="headerlink" title="吴文萱"></a>吴文萱</h4><p><img src="img/%E6%9D%B0%E8%A5%BF%E8%AE%B2%E6%95%85%E4%BA%8B.assets/IMG_20200103_154535.jpg" alt="和吴文萱一起在顺德吃双皮奶、芝麻糊"></p><p>吴文萱也是我在贝赛思最好的朋友之一。我们的关系挺微妙的，按照时间线大概是“朋友-男女朋友-朋友”的关系，应该属于比较少有的分手之后还能继续当好朋友的情况吧。</p><p>我本来想用“情侣”描述中间那段时间的关系，但回想一下，中间那段时间，我们俩在其实很大程度上并没有像典型的”情侣“那样的关系，所以想了一下还是叫”男女朋友“吧。那段时间是我们俩交流最密切的一段时间了，我觉得造就这段关系的原因大概有两个：吴文萱在那段时间对计算机相关的东西特别感兴趣，我又喜欢教别人技术相关的东西，所以她自然就跟我有了点话题；另一个原因是我们俩在那段时间各自都受到不同的压力，需要找个人倾诉，我们又互相愿意倾诉和倾听，所以就有聊头了。那真是一段快乐的时光啊，我觉得要是没有这段特殊的经历，我的高中生活大概要暗淡、阴郁得多吧。总之，我真的非常感谢吴文萱能陪我一起度过这段时光，也希望我们的友谊能一直延续下去吧。</p><h4 id="陈泽新"><a href="#陈泽新" class="headerlink" title="陈泽新"></a>陈泽新</h4><p><img src="img/%E6%9D%B0%E8%A5%BF%E8%AE%B2%E6%95%85%E4%BA%8B.assets/WeChat_Image_20210324225252.jpg" alt="在后面开心到模糊的我"></p><p>说到我的朋友们，当然不能落下和我同住 3 年的舍友陈泽新了。</p><p>克里斯让我最难忘的特征，莫过于他的豪放了。他总是喜欢一见到我，不分场合和地点，老远地就用粤语叫我的名字——“嘉曦！”（嘎嘿！）。我的名字大概是他说得最标准的一句粤语了吧（想想还是挺荣幸的呢）。</p><p>宿舍是一个神奇的地方，它似乎能把任何住在一起的人拉拢到一起聊天。我和陈泽新在晚上无聊的时候几乎也是无话不聊——从最新发布的科技产品，到各自对某些事物的看法和吐槽，全都在聊天的范围之内。在宿舍里开这种小型夜谈会真的是住宿学生独享的一种快乐啊。</p><p>而不开夜谈会的晚上，通常就是听歌的晚上了。陈奕迅是陈泽新最喜欢的歌手，三年来我们俩不知道循环过多少遍他的歌。有时我们听着听着就情不自禁地唱了起来，那气氛是一个人塞着耳朵听歌得不到的。</p><h4 id="一起玩的伙伴们"><a href="#一起玩的伙伴们" class="headerlink" title="一起玩的伙伴们"></a>一起玩的伙伴们</h4><p><img src="img/%E6%9D%B0%E8%A5%BF%E8%AE%B2%E6%95%85%E4%BA%8B.assets/IMG_20200806_165749_01.jpg" alt="一起在长隆玩，此时郑天乐正在和李飘玩过山车"></p><p>在这个部分，我要写的伙伴们就很多了，包括但不限于凌宇骏、叶欣奕、田雨禾、郑天乐、罗淳熙等（排名不分先后）。</p><p>这些伙伴们都是我平时比较玩得来的，也时不时回在周末约到一起去玩。我不算特别能社交的人，所以这大概就算我高中时期比较广的社交圈了吧。虽然大家性格、爱好等等似乎都各不相同，但大家竟然意外地玩得来。每次一起出外玩都会玩得疯疯癫癫，不亦乐乎。能有那么一群可以一起快乐玩耍的小伙伴们，真的是我的一种幸运啊。</p><h4 id="全年级同学"><a href="#全年级同学" class="headerlink" title="全年级同学"></a>全年级同学</h4><p>（找不到照片）</p><p>虽然说我和年级里面很多人都不是很熟，但是毕竟是一起待了四年的同学啊，多多少少都由不同程度的认识。</p><p>这么多同学里，我曾经找过我帮忙的应该不在少数，我也很乐意去帮。我自己似乎也接受了“工具人”这个设定，希望以后也还能多多帮到大家吧。</p><h3 id="我最想感谢的老师们"><a href="#我最想感谢的老师们" class="headerlink" title="我最想感谢的老师们"></a>我最想感谢的老师们</h3><p>由于不善言辞，我心中的千言万语和感谢之意可能无法被短短的文字表达出来，还请谅解！</p><h4 id="Miro-Jurisic"><a href="#Miro-Jurisic" class="headerlink" title="Miro Jurisic"></a>Miro Jurisic</h4><p>米罗，可能是我最喜欢的老师了。他也是严格意义上我的编程启蒙老师（在上他的计算机科学课之前我一直没有系统地学习过编程）。毫不夸张地说，我认为他宽松的教学方式是最适合教计算机的方式了。学习就该像他的课堂那样培养兴趣，并让学生们自由地去探索。这大概就是我喜欢他的原因吧。虽然米罗可能看不懂中文，但是我还是想对他说一句“谢谢”。</p><h4 id="Fleur-Gooden"><a href="#Fleur-Gooden" class="headerlink" title="Fleur Gooden"></a>Fleur Gooden</h4><p>Ms. Gooden 和米罗则大有不同，在大多数情况下是一个比较严谨、严格的老师（当然她也有幽默的时候）。我是最后一年才认识她的，在她的计算机科学课上当了一年助教。我非常感谢她能给我一个这么好的学习和实践的机会，也感谢她在其它各个方面给予我的种种支持和帮助。</p><h4 id="苏冬芸"><a href="#苏冬芸" class="headerlink" title="苏冬芸"></a>苏冬芸</h4><p>苏迪，人人都爱的老师。优点我就不多赘述了（我也不会夸人）。苏老师的语文课真的给我带来了不少学习语文的快乐，我也一直都非常享受上她的语文课。我也不说多的了，总之就是非常感谢苏老师！</p><h4 id="Dan-Schneider"><a href="#Dan-Schneider" class="headerlink" title="Dan Schneider"></a>Dan Schneider</h4><p>Mr. 施耐德是我从 9 年级一直跟到 12 年级的老师了。这四年间他曾经教我经济学，带领 NHS，以及给升学做准备。他不断地给予我各个方面的帮助、鼓励、关怀，还给了我许多机会。所以我对 Mr. Schneider 也是相当感激的。谢谢你！</p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
    <summary type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;写在前面&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#写在前面&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;写在前面&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;写在前面&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;一开始让我做这个毕业项目的时候我是毫无头绪的，看同学们各种各样的项目，我真的想不到我能做些什么——有的同学给所有人都定制一份</summary>
      
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Basis" scheme="https://www.jessexu.me/tags/Basis/"/>
    
    <category term="中文" scheme="https://www.jessexu.me/tags/%E4%B8%AD%E6%96%87/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>编程笔记 - Java 多线程</title>
    <link href="https://www.jessexu.me/2019/%E7%BC%96%E7%A8%8B%E7%AC%94%E8%AE%B0-Java%E5%A4%9A%E7%BA%BF%E7%A8%8B/"/>
    <id>https://www.jessexu.me/2019/%E7%BC%96%E7%A8%8B%E7%AC%94%E8%AE%B0-Java%E5%A4%9A%E7%BA%BF%E7%A8%8B/</id>
    <published>2019-01-20T12:50:14.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-01-20T12:50:14.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>最近在学校的 NHS* 里做一个有趣的项目——为学校的“赌场之夜”做两个老虎机，编写过程中遇到了些困难，最终学习了 Java 的多线程相关的知识然后解决了问题。</p><span id="more"></span><p>故事：我们学校的 NHS 开展了一个 Project，就是要以“赌场”为主题，举办一个 Winter Formal (“冬季舞会”)。我负责做两台老虎机。本来想偷懒，直接上网上找开源的 HTML5 的实现，但我的计算机老师鼓励我自己用 Java 实现，不要用现成的。我都想好怎么编了，编出来之后竟然不 work，本来应该是动画的地方只出现了转圈圈，程序冻住几秒，并没有按照预期播放动画。经过思考之后，学习了多线程的知识，然后解决了问题。就此记录该过程。</p><hr><p>一开始遇到的问题是这样的：写好了动画的代码，用 Thread.sleep(time) 来实现动画，但是运行的时候却只有鼠标转圈圈，没有动画，但是等几秒后（“动画”完成后），摇奖的结果会显示。估计是运行的时候 Thread 还没有更新 GUI 里面的的内容就 Sleep 了，或者是不是应该叫做被“阻塞”了？此时程序的情况如下图：</p><p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/mgrddsj/PicLib/master/One%20Thread.gif"></p><p>于是我就上 YouTube 上面找 Java 多线程相关的教程，找到如下这个<a href="https://youtu.be/VYN-CBtPNiM">视频</a>（26和27集连起来看）。同时发现这个<a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/thenewboston">频道</a>有挺多编程相关的教程的，Java、Python……什么都有。推荐一下。（需要梯子）</p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/VYN-CBtPNiM" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>其实就是在原来 GUI 的 class 之外再加一个 class（把原来的 Spin 相关的内容迁移到新的 class 里面，然后在 GUI class 里面提供 accessor method 以供修改显示的图片）。第二个 class 要在 class name 后面加上 implements Runnable ，同时把要运行的那段代码放在一个叫 run 的 method 里面（ IDE 会自动提示加上 import java.awt.EventQueue; ）。然后在 GUI class 里面加上下面的代码就行了（我的第二个 class 的名字叫做 “spin”）。<figure class="highlight java"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">Thread t1 = <span class="keyword">new</span> Thread(<span class="keyword">new</span> Spin(board,slot1Res,slot2Res,slot3Res));</span><br><span class="line">t1.start();</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure><p>改好之后程序的程序的架构大概是这样的：</p><p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/mgrddsj/PicLib/master/Two%20Threads.gif"></p><p>[^NHS]: National Honors Society</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;最近在学校的 NHS* 里做一个有趣的项目——为学校的“赌场之夜”做两个老虎机，编写过程中遇到了些困难，最终学习了 Java 的多线程相关的知识然后解决了问题。&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    <category term="折腾" scheme="https://www.jessexu.me/categories/%E6%8A%98%E8%85%BE/"/>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>再见2018！你好2019！</title>
    <link href="https://www.jessexu.me/2019/%E5%86%8D%E8%A7%812018%EF%BC%81%E4%BD%A0%E5%A5%BD2019%EF%BC%81/"/>
    <id>https://www.jessexu.me/2019/%E5%86%8D%E8%A7%812018%EF%BC%81%E4%BD%A0%E5%A5%BD2019%EF%BC%81/</id>
    <published>2019-01-09T12:43:11.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-01-10T13:00:00.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="2018总结及2019计划"><a href="#2018总结及2019计划" class="headerlink" title="2018总结及2019计划"></a>2018总结及2019计划</h1><p>这其实是一篇学校中文课要求的作业，那我也借此机会，辞旧迎新，发布真正意义上的这个博客的第一篇文章吧</p><span id="more"></span><h1 id="再见，2018！"><a href="#再见，2018！" class="headerlink" title="再见，2018！"></a>再见，2018！</h1><p>2018，说忙不忙，但是也不轻松。回想2018，我除了努力学习，竟然想不到别的东西……看来真的是沉迷学习，<del>日渐消瘦</del>（并没有）了。这一年，我考了人生中头三场AP考试，第一次感受到了GPA带来的学习压力，也第一次体验到了国际学校所带来的与众不同的压力。而我以前在省附（天河省实）的同学们也都升到了各个不同的高中，我听说他们的压力也很大，只不过和我受到的压力有点不同。但我明白了，在这个年龄段，没有谁是可以不努力的，没有谁的压力小，大家虽然有不同的方向、不同的目标，但是<del>掉发</del> 辛苦是不可少的。</p><p>除了学习，我也有很多别的经历。我打开Google Photos （谷歌相册）翻了一番，发现里面满满的都是各种回忆——去了两次日本，一次赏樱花+滑雪，一次在京阪神周边转悠。我们全家都很喜欢日本这个国家，也去过好多次了，但是还是很喜欢去——又干净，人又有礼貌，风景又漂亮，又有独特的文化，每次去都会有不同的体验。我个人也有喜欢日本的独特理由，那里的空气，对我这种鼻炎患者太友好了。我又喜欢喝冰水，日本到处都有冰水喝😂…不知道为什么，身边有些人似乎对日本有些偏见，有点抗拒。我在这里多说一句，我觉得爱国是好的，是一个团结的民族应有的特征。但是不能盲目爱国，始终要客观地看待事实。</p><p>（之后补些旅游的照片上来，我这个博客的封面图也是今年在日本拍的）</p><p>这一年，我也变得更独立了（可能吧？）。我才发现我长这么大了，基本上出街都是父母陪着的。今年我有两次和同学约着自己出去玩，感觉挺不一样的。没有了那么多的约束，更能放开来玩，但也更考验我的自控能力。所幸我也是个“乖宝宝”，我还是可以照顾好自己的。我觉得我也早就是时候脱离“妈宝”这个角色了，毕竟我总是要独立的嘛。</p><p>2018年大概就这么点事吧，总的来说是很丰富多彩的一年。</p><h1 id="你好，2019！"><a href="#你好，2019！" class="headerlink" title="你好，2019！"></a>你好，2019！</h1><p>“新年新气象”，我也来<del>立flag</del> 做新年的计划</p><h3 id="减肥"><a href="#减肥" class="headerlink" title="减肥"></a>减肥</h3><p>减肥当然是必不可少的，这好像是我每一年必有的计划😥。我当然是希望能减下来啊，但是…先吃饱了才有力气减肥啊！</p><h3 id="考好AP"><a href="#考好AP" class="headerlink" title="考好AP"></a>考好AP</h3><p>今年所选的AP科目对于我来说都有一定的挑战性和难度，加上我准备重考去年考差了的AP Physics 1，今年的压力就很大了。我还是要加油！</p><h3 id="争取搞定托福"><a href="#争取搞定托福" class="headerlink" title="争取搞定托福"></a>争取搞定托福</h3><p>争取在今年内搞定托福吧，不能再拖了，加之很多夏校都要求提交托福成绩，托福还是挺重要的。</p><h3 id="坚持更新博客"><a href="#坚持更新博客" class="headerlink" title="坚持更新博客"></a>坚持更新博客</h3><p>这个博客刚开没多久，尽管没有多少人看，我也要保持更新。这将是对我的责任心的培养。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;2018总结及2019计划&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2018总结及2019计划&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;2018总结及2019计划&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;2018总结及2019计划&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;这其实是一篇学校中文课要求的作业，那我也借此机会，辞旧迎新，发布真正意义上的这个博客的第一篇文章吧&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    <category term="奇思妙想" scheme="https://www.jessexu.me/categories/%E5%A5%87%E6%80%9D%E5%A6%99%E6%83%B3/"/>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>关于此博客</title>
    <link href="https://www.jessexu.me/2018/12/02/%E5%85%B3%E4%BA%8E%E6%AD%A4%E5%8D%9A%E5%AE%A2/"/>
    <id>https://www.jessexu.me/2018/12/02/%E5%85%B3%E4%BA%8E%E6%AD%A4%E5%8D%9A%E5%AE%A2/</id>
    <published>2018-12-02T08:58:49.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-12-26T13:58:53.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[置顶文章]</p><h2 id="介绍"><a href="#介绍" class="headerlink" title="介绍"></a>介绍</h2><p>在这个博客之前，我其实已经有过3-4个博客了——都放弃了…</p><p>最近又心血来潮，想写点东西，就开了这么个博客。<br>这也是一件好事——让我学习一下怎么样坚持一件事情。</p><p>这个博客里面的博文大多数都会比较短，<del>因为我懒</del> ，同时大家读起来也比较方便。</p><span id="more"></span><h2 id="为什么开博客网站，而不用现成的？"><a href="#为什么开博客网站，而不用现成的？" class="headerlink" title="为什么开博客网站，而不用现成的？"></a>为什么开博客网站，而不用现成的？</h2><p>主要是不想受到平台的限制，比如说微博、微信、简书等等平台都有各种各样的限制，各种花哨的东西太多了，我不想去研究平台的规则，只是想安安静静自己写点东西而已。</p><p>还有就是想有个性一点，建一个网站的话可以有自己的域名，显得很高大上😂。文章数据也可控一些，不会无法导出。</p><p>不过为了大家容易访问，以后可能也会考虑开一个微信公众号😄。</p><h2 id="博客里会有什么东西？"><a href="#博客里会有什么东西？" class="headerlink" title="博客里会有什么东西？"></a>博客里会有什么东西？</h2><p>杂七杂八，什么东西都可能有。</p><p>目前想到的几大主题：</p><ul><li><p><a href="https://www.jessexu.me/categories/%E4%BC%98%E9%9B%85/">优雅</a></p></li><li><p>如何优雅、高效地使用电脑 </p><p><a href="https://www.jessexu.me/2018/%E5%85%B3%E4%BA%8E%E4%BC%98%E9%9B%85%E6%A0%8F%E7%9B%AE/">(点我跳到栏目介绍)</a></p></li><li><p><a href="https://www.jessexu.me/categories/%E6%8A%98%E8%85%BE/">折腾</a></p></li><li><p>一些折腾/搞机的心得、教程</p><p><a href="https://www.jessexu.me/2018/%E5%85%B3%E4%BA%8E%E6%8A%98%E8%85%BE%E6%A0%8F%E7%9B%AE/">(点我跳到栏目介绍)</a></p></li><li><p><a href="https://www.jessexu.me/categories/%E6%AF%8F%E5%91%A8%E4%B8%80%E9%94%AE/">每周一键</a></p></li><li><p>每个星期向大家介绍一个快捷键</p><p><a href="https://www.jessexu.me/2018/%E5%85%B3%E4%BA%8E%E6%AF%8F%E5%91%A8%E4%B8%80%E9%94%AE%E6%A0%8F%E7%9B%AE/">(点我跳到栏目介绍)</a></p></li><li><p><a href="https://www.jessexu.me/categories/%E5%A5%87%E6%80%9D%E5%A6%99%E6%83%B3/">奇思妙想</a></p></li><li><p>这个主题不谈科技，只是生活中的一些奇思妙想</p><p><a href="https://www.jessexu.me/2019/%E5%85%B3%E4%BA%8E%E5%A5%87%E6%80%9D%E5%A6%99%E6%83%B3%E6%A0%8F%E7%9B%AE/">(点我跳到栏目介绍)</a></p></li><li><p><a href="https://www.jessexu.me/categories/%E8%B5%84%E6%BA%90%E5%88%86%E4%BA%AB/">资源分享</a></p><ul><li>分享一些资源</li></ul><p> <a href="https://www.jessexu.me/2019/%E5%85%B3%E4%BA%8E%E8%B5%84%E6%BA%90%E5%88%86%E4%BA%AB%E6%A0%8F%E7%9B%AE/">(点我跳到栏目介绍)</a></p></li><li><p><a href="https://www.jessexu.me/categories/PowerPoint/">PowerPoint</a></p></li><li><p>给大家分享一些做PPT的经验，可能会送一些好看的PPT</p><p><a href="https://www.jessexu.me/2019/%E5%85%B3%E4%BA%8EPowerPoint%E6%A0%8F%E7%9B%AE/">(点我跳到栏目介绍)</a></p></li></ul>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;[置顶文章]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;介绍&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#介绍&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;介绍&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;介绍&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;在这个博客之前，我其实已经有过3-4个博客了——都放弃了…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;最近又心血来潮，想写点东西，就开了这么个博客。&lt;br&gt;这也是一件好事——让我学习一下怎么样坚持一件事情。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这个博客里面的博文大多数都会比较短，&lt;del&gt;因为我懒&lt;/del&gt; ，同时大家读起来也比较方便。&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
